hello everybody Marcus here just want to
do let you know about a new podcast I'm
working on it's called Omega tau that
Omega tau podcast top net and it's about
all kinds of things
science and technology that I find
interesting first episode is on flying
gliders episode number two is on whether
data measurement number three is on
cancer research number four is on
commercial spaceflight and spaceship one
and number five is about earth race
around the world in a powerboat some of
the episodes are German some are English
there is a fee for everything and there
is a separate feed for English episodes
so why don't you go to omekata podcast
up net download some episodes let me
know what you think thanks and have fun
listening
[Music]
soft engineering radio episode 119 DSL
in practice with JP tall one
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hello everybody to this new episode of
software engineering radio this episode
is about domain-specific languages in
practice we've recorded it at the code
generation 2008 conference so you're
probably not surprised that it's about
languages and code generations it's a
discussion with you Hapuku
1209 JP : and from Medicus they have
been doing this meta language code
generator stuff for years before we
actually get started let me let me just
say one thing as you probably know from
past episodes of the podcast and also
maybe generally from my website or
something this whole model driven
domain-specific languages thing is near
and dear to my heart so I have quite a
couple of opinions myself so this
episode is more a discussion between me
and JP so I sometimes cannot hold back
with my own opinion I hope that's okay
I couldn't resist I think it makes the
discussion more interesting but if you
don't like that if you consider me more
like a normal interview or a journalist
then you might probably or perhaps be a
little bit annoyed anyway have fun with
the episode and welcome JP to the
episode thank you great pleasure to be
here yeah if we've planned this for
quite a while yes so JP why don't you
introduce yourself to our listeners my
name is Rebecca I have been working with
metamodeling and a specific graphical
language and code generator since 1991
and resulted in a company called
Medicaid
and we have been building these
languages and generators mostly tools
support for that since then right so so
what we are going to talk about
obviously then is how to build languages
how to put generators it's this whole
model driven DSL topic and just to give
you lead reader readers well I should
have learned this by now so I took a few
listeners a heads up about the specifics
we've had episodes on model driven
development a while ago I think it was
episodes 5 & 6 a long time ago and we've
also had other stuff on internal dsls
and meta programming so in this episode
we want to focus primarily on some of
the experiences and the practical
concerns that arise once you want to
scale this to to really larger projects
and I guess that's also where you guys
have a lot of experience yes so why
don't we start by briefly recapping what
it's about what does it matter model
what is it you know graphical versus
textual syntax why don't you give us a
little brief heads up how you see this
world I noticed in listen good podcast
you had earlier just want to basically
say what kind of domain-specific
languages we are working with yep so we
are mostly applying almost always
external domain-specific languages and
they scale better because there's no
escape to the host language
we also focus on mostly on graphical
domain-specific languages but some are
also matrix or table based and usually
they have some embedded text naturally
in yellow as well
the other key issue what we did well we
did indeed in that way in the right
first place in 1991 is that we have
first multiple separate individual
domain-specific languages and then we
figure out that usually you we need to
combine them so another thing we do is
we have a multiple integrated external
domain-specific languages so we can
share data between models based on
different languages and support group
group working so another way of saying
that is that you support the definition
of several viewpoints with separate
syntaxes for the same overall model
correct right correct but nothing
prevents to to keep those models for
different users totally but still the
modeling concept and power I see so that
goes back to the repository stuff you
talked about in a minute and our aim is
basically why we have been successful
with this is that we always try to do a
full cogeneration from the modelers
perspective meaning that if someone
creates a model then he can generate a
code that doesn't need to be any more
touched afterwards yeah I mean we have
obviously we've talked many times and
that's one point where I kind of think
that's hard to always do I mean issue
sure but if there's some number of ways
to do that I'm trying to reach that
situation right okay most typical is
that you have other people who already
develop some domain framework code
additionally yeah oh you have exiting
platforms that are already kappa before
and there's a lot of rule engines and
such you can specify the rules
that's quite graphically saying
declarative matter what kind of business
rules you would write run how you would
like to guide your telephone calls yeah
to handle like service creation and
those areas it works fine but let me let
me give an example that the typical wall
right say we have a state machine it's
of course easy to draw diagrams with you
know rectangles and and of course with
rounded corners and transition arrows
but if you have a guard condition which
can be any arbitrary expression in
whatever expression language then I
think there are only two choices one
choices you put the expression as a
string in the model yes which is often
not that great because you have no code
completion or syntax acting or you you
somehow write that in some manual code
snippet that you then integrate with the
generated overall state machine what's
your what's your take on that we
basically see in a mm all approach is
one is of course is adding a string
right to to exiting model that's a the
last resort yeah always works in do the
other approach do we know about the type
of conditions or whatever the yeah
so we then can then a little bit
classify or type then I see and then
they become again part of the modeling
language with a widget the other extreme
yeah and there's these middle solutions
that you have already implemented
solution to libraries for these typical
cardi conditions or whatever they would
be yeah and then you integrate from your
models to those existing yeah components
right okay so you what you would do is
you would have a library with when you
manually written code with cons read you
give them names yes and you just mention
the name in the model that will be warm
yes it yeah but but I mean I mean now we
were actually almost philosophical right
because what I would do is I would
generate some kind of skeleton with a
method blah if the cone the guard
condition is called blah yes and then I
fill in the code what you say is we
first write the BLA method put it in a
library and then mention it if you have
exiting a framework or platform yeah and
component library then that's usually
you would like to do you realize that
there's something that multiple people
would like to use but if you would is
there even if it's only one person who
need yeah then it's always possible
still to generate the protected blocks
so you you make o generate you do that
well we tool allows to do that yep so
you make a code generator where you the
person who makes a generator says that
have card conditions or something that
we you would like to write later on to
the generated code yep so the person
says that this is the block yeah but you
can change later on okay so it's
actually not that far apart but but we
we don't recommend people to do that I
mostly because in a large-scale use so
if you have external DSL we want to hire
the complexity we want to make
development easier and we have a hundred
guys who are making designs sure someone
will not write inside the protector look
now I agree and you should avoid this
stuff and you should put as much as
possible in the model and you should try
to reach 100% cogeneration but there are
situations when you can't sure and and
then you need you need a plan B and I
think we just outlined and there are
multiple options and little bit depends
your situation what your plan B actually
looks like yeah of course yes but I
guess I think I interrupted you when you
were talking about I guess you were
getting at this interpretation versus
cogeneration off the tool itself yes I
was actually these were two two other
bullets at eye-rolling right sorry is
that what we do is we treat the
metamodel language definition dsl
definition as a data and then we don't
generate tool support we already have an
existing tool that actually reads this
metamodel yep and then builds these
specific editors based on the existing
metamodel data and this is important all
four to two things we didn't do that in
the right in this way in the first place
and we learned that in in industry use
people who create these metals they want
to be sure that the language creation
and language modification tasks are safe
because if they have let's say 100
developers who are creating models and
then they change the metamodel therefore
how do they'll may be a little bit
worried about what will happen to the
existing models it's the language
evolution preventing evolution and then
we can currenty that look you can change
the metamodel
whatever you like the tool will know
what kind of changes you can do and you
can't broke others models yep
so they still upload load you can see
the models and in many cases they're
just update automatically today existing
models yeah and just to contrast that
with for example EMF or gmf the problem
depending on what kind of changes you do
is that if you build your meta model in
a given way and then generate for
example java code from it
an editor that that is implemented in
Java and then you change the metamodel
it might happen that your that your
editor slashed the EMF library whatever
isn't able to load the model anymore
because the models storage structure has
been baked into the generated source
code and that that's clearly a problem
and that's obviously for for industry
use if you have a lot of models existing
we can't really go and say back to the
modelers to please start again yeah
because the metamodel changed well you
you don't have to start again but you
have to set it to incase of EMF you
might have to patch the underlying xmi
which is of course also ugly yeah okay
but basically try to streamline this
project that's absolutely yeah the other
thing is so did you did you finish yeah
yes okay so let's go back briefly to
those different viewpoints because
that's something I found to be very very
important in practice that people really
specifically think about the fact that a
real system is built from several
different viewpoints and you have
typically different tiers else or
different languages one of them might be
your manually written code that that
actually assembles the overall system so
so can you talk a little bit about how
you do this technology wise you know
repository and and and the different
viewpoints and how it all works on one
thing and still represents differently
to different uses of viewpoints we
basically differ in the two things the
concepts or structure we call it
abstract syntax and also for models and
then concrete impact they're two totally
different things and it always should
start from dear abstract syntax yep and
we basically specify the metamodel but
in our meta modeling language we have a
specific concepts like a language so we
can identify what you call viewpoints be
identified what kind of viewpoints you
would like to have for instance you
would like to have a display view
another one would be a navigation view a
persistence view or or or real-time view
whatever those beautiful be but then we
can identify different kind of modelers
or model the usage scenarios that we
need
to have this kind of language for
describing static structures another one
for describing behavior structures yet
the models that are created with these
two languages still share the same data
so if someone changes the data in a
static view and it's applied also in the
behavioral view it automatically updates
in that peer review as to suppose
refactoring a model model editing work
yeah so in contrast I'm contrasting with
some other tooling just to make the
point if you did that for example what
I'm typically it depends on how you do
it with the EMF but classically you
might have literally different models
and then if you generate code you you
load all of them somehow join them make
sure you you you you know you establish
connections between things that actually
are the same thing or that reference
each other and then you write a code
generator that that kind of takes all of
that in and and and build steel rod so
from this quarry and that seems to be
one interest for this model to model
transformations that you can combine
things and you can work with them to
later produce them whereas our ideas to
do the integration not so much on the
cogeneration phase but you can do it
also at the modeling
yeah I'm yep that's actually another
point where we tend to disagree a little
bit which is the the importance rate of
model to model runs all agents yeah so
you don't have them in the tool right
you can do model to model transformation
we even do model to metal transformation
but you can do such a things through
intermediate four months of such weather
usually that we don't have found that
customers really need so in other words
what you're doing is you you generate
with a code generator the textual XML
probably representation of the thing you
are of the model you are trying to
transform to yes if you want to do that
to more yes
there's also API so if you want to use
Excel to do that okay you can you can
use Excel and macros and do the same
thing okay at the at the repository
level so you can remove data from the
repository new models yeah okay okay if
if you think that you will need to have
a such a kind of thing we just feel that
it's better if the the dings are
reintegrated at the modeling time
because
and refactoring a model working is
easier that because we can see where the
changes happened so in our situation if
you see that something is changing in
the data model you can see maybe already
that this is shared by somewhere else
you can ask where it is and then you can
see another diagram where the data is
has further details yeah III as I said I
tend to disagree at ten
no I don't disagree with what you said
but I have a lot of scenarios where
models run some errands are as really
useful but I guess that's the topic for
a different episode I'm not sure I
should like put my bad thing but they
feel look viewpoints of of a consultant
yeah and a viewpoint of a tool already
their perspectives are different so
consultants of course want to reuse
exiting generators if they have already
done something for example for a formal
point of view to vendor point of view
customer have already done on their own
code generator they don't want to share
that with a competitor yeah so vision
less need to work with here since we're
discussing it already I mean one of them
oh one of the areas where I think it's
kind of really useful is if you like if
you think in terms of product lines if
you consider a state machine model you
always use it as an example because
everybody knows it and there is a
variant of your state machine you want
to be able to sell for an extra price
and that variant has what I call the
emergency stop feature so we have like
50 states and from each of them you want
the new transition with the event stop
that goes to a failsafe State now how do
you change how do you get those 50
additional transfer transitions into
your otherwise manually translate
machine model so you want that all those
state machines have a connection to a
machine G yes all states in the state
machine but then and then I wouldn't
model that at all right was everybody
has that you want to draw 50 lines which
is stupid yes yeah but now here's the
thing the generated code if you have an
execution thingy that it has to have
those things now you can put this into
your code generator
sure but it would be property of that
whole state machine to say in this state
machine all these states have the
emergency yeah but it should be that's
that's an boolean value in that whole
state machine diagram will these states
has emergency prophecy okay or each
individual state could have this
property and by default that property
could be yes I have an event solutely
absolutely but now now you set this
boolean flag to true that the boolean
every state needs to have the emergency
you set this to do so now what but you
still need to generate the the code that
actually imagined the state machine
generated as a big switch-case thing for
it now all those 50 state cases need to
have this additional branch to this so
how do you get it in there what you
would do is basically you would say in
your code generator is this boolean flag
is set to true then generate something
else and I think that's that's a problem
and the reason why and I think that is
is your code generator typically says
something like for each state in my
model generating an integer constant for
each state in my model also generate a
case block in my switch statement and so
on my point is you have this algorithmic
part of the generator and in the
generator
yes that that iterates over the model
now if you want to do your boolean flag
then you always have the algorithmic
part and after that you say and also if
this thing is true then you have this
additional integer constant the
additional case blog and so on and that
complicates your generator and if you do
model to model transformation just one
sentence more what you will do is if
this boolean flag is set to true you
take your model as it is you with the
transformation add those 50 additional
transitions and then you just run the
generator without the generator caring
about the fact that there are special
emergency things and without this
without these ifs in the generator and
stuff and that's really a nice
modularization well you could no more
sentences but a solution for that in
from our angle would be that you realize
that there are the specific emergency
states transitions
other kind of state transitions
somewhere you have a generator who knows
how to handle state transitions yes so
it doesn't need to be in this state but
information you can abstract that into a
common sub protein so whenever you are
generating code it looks all the doc top
type of things for this traitor state
transition and then only in that place
you also looked at emergency sure but
it's scattered you have in a typical you
have several places where you would have
to do it but every yes okay so could be
but then you you could have a multiple
places in your code generator where you
can call out other the existing routine
so the idea comes how you structure your
code generator and you can structure it
many ways per file per sectional file
usually we see most people do it they
start the structure the generator based
on each domain concept so when they have
a different language concepts they have
one generator for each concept then
later they may look that well actually
this has some multiple commonalities
with other concepts yep and then they
refactor the generator but again it's
it's a work done by a couple of persons
right all the rest modelers don't do
that so if it is hard for if it's hard
to do this emergency will generate okay
okay it's a hard only for one or two
guys that's true that's always true most
of all words that you hear making
culture making compilers also yeah but I
mean harder so and I promise we're
getting to the end of this discussion
now soon but I think my experience is
once you went once your code generator
grows and once you do a lot of product
line stuff where you have many of these
optional features that depend that that
change your code generator the
complexity of your code generator
becomes an issue not an unsolvable issue
one thing to do that to solve is that
trying to raise the level of abstraction
or really the modeling language so you
can put more rules of the modeling
language and so that the coaching rater
becomes smaller
yeah the same thing if people have
problems with generating code from pure
class diagrams yeah sure
because then the cop the person who
makes a generator it can be that half of
the coach and wrappers just checking if
the input that I get from the UML
diagram has the guy who created it has
it filled the properties correct answer
and and that kind of thing otherwise we
are generating padding so if we can put
to the meta multi rules to the language
the the code generator can cut into half
the size
I'm not saying you cannot solve some of
these things without model
transformations of course you can you do
it works if you are I'm just saying
having mod transformations as an
additional entry in your toolkit is
useful sure because in that case the
only thing you'd have to do is you write
like seven lines of model transformation
that adds those additional emergency
stop things and you don't even touch
your code generator and you don't even
touch your model and you don't even
touch your Matt Hamill yes it's
extremely nicely localized and that's my
whole point you you may apply those if
they make sense yes we have found out in
many cases you don't need those as well
and makes the process much easier so for
understanding do and of course many
people do even the worst thing that you
don't do but many people do the thing
that they modify the models during this
translation process yeah let's go oh em
gee em da ting which which will never
work
yeah so just to clarify what you were
talking about is you have a PIM right
yeah yeah and you transform it into
let's say a PS m and then you go into
the PSM change things add things at the
correction additional stuff and then you
continue generating and that won't work
because it's impossible to version and
handle and people people don't know how
how the deal will change is in case of
they need to regenerate the PSM model
it's the protected region problem on
model on models correct so okay end of
sidetrack what we want to do in the rest
of this episode is we want to look at a
couple of experience from your practical
work with real customers you've been
around for a while so you have a couple
of them so do we want to do two things
you want to look at a couple of example
language --is and then discuss why that
has been successful couple of metrics
couple of best practices the challenge
with these examples is that
unfortunately the best examples are
something that are done by our customers
it's totaled a IPR sure they would come
and kill us if we show they languages
because you can see from the metamodel
everything would tape yeah and to do
yeah right
yeah so that's why we don't see luckily
we're in an audio medium where we can
enjoy anyway so so the first case we're
looking here looking at here is
insurance stuff and I find that
interesting because I have worked in the
insurance domain also and what is
interesting is that the cases I have
seen was that we use textual languages
so I'm surprised or whatever that that
it kind of is useful to use graphical
languages in the insurance domain so
what did you actually described with
those graphical languages different kind
of financial products ahead insurance
product in this particle case and this
is a broker for insurance products
providing web portal people can compare
insurance products of different type so
let's say that if I have a car and my
car is at night in cash do I get a
better discount for the thief Yeah right
but whatever but you're right the same
kind of rules also than it takes to Lee
also Capgemini has been working with the
bit something with deal with the pension
rules you can excel so she'd faced
well that was old and now they've done
intentional stuff and of course that's
what of what I was referring to yes yes
okay okay that's fine yeah and and they
already had a domain model to think they
call domain model which means this is
what all insurances are route yep and
for some reason they had defined it by
using a move yep and they asked and you
then we would like now that people
insurance experts can specify insurance
products so that they could then
generate code out of the models in this
case Java code into j2e website and that
code is used to actually execute the
calculations and if people heads-up on
how much they're gonna get how much you
have to pay correct correct
I think this is interesting because
unlike many people think that this
modern stuff is only relevant for like
technical people but this is really used
by domain expert ana and to be totally
honest here we were also surprised yeah
that the that once we heard
the the the language that they they
asked us to to code evil with them is
something that they give for
non-technical people they give it from
two insurance experts to specify so
that's not Joe insurance sales guy it's
rather the experts that actually define
the contract correct yeah so these are
are these mathematicians or I mean these
are structured thinking people structure
to get that's true but not conceptual
thinking people nice yes yes and who
actually built the language did they do
that actually we in this particular case
we did that for them okay so they had
the domain model they have the MEF move
rattle and they said can you put this
into a language yeah and we asked them
like here what the language would look
like so we are looking here slide with
the concrete syntax of different traffic
signs and so they asked them to specify
how they would like to look that earth
because then it becomes their language
yeah sure yes and then we implement
these rules together with this Java
generator and we did that in 11 days if
I remember correctly and it was quickly
done partly because they already had a
good domain model right so the knowledge
was already there structured it was just
about building the the UI that nice Airy
feeling building only the language
because yeah building the editors and
building to generate them using the
concrete syntax of course the when they
had the metamodel
specified by mufe class diagram it
didn't have all the rules for yes and
only later when when you tried out with
them they realize no you can't make a
such thing our domain model don't have
this rule because domain mu is just a
piece of paper not something they run
yeah now they can run the domain model
and then they realize that now they need
to specify it correctly because it's
executing here so what's interesting
here is that this is a case that shows
that one way of getting to a good
language is that you just take the
existing concepts and stuff that domain
experts already have and and formalize
them into a tool correct do you know of
and that's of course somehow ideal
because you already know what to do yes
do you have thoughts about what other
approaches there are to come up with a
good domain language or or DSL we bro
the boo you can plug it we'll put it in
the show notes we wrote a book on on
these and actually a paper for software
product lines a couple of years ago to
look how people are building languages
and one of them works that they already
have a stop list domain work couple
reader main concepts like here like here
and they would like to apply it yeah
the other kind of thing is that the the
product has a clear physical structure
like let's say a home automation a
stopwatch neonate no stopwatch is going
to have an example here my mind that
that you have a clear structure let's
say a battleship communication system F
or forklift in a in a lorry you can see
that okay it has so many still interests
and so forth that's your language yeah
the other sort of domain-specific
languages are those which are based on
look or feel or hear of the system yeah
so like user interface right dedicated
telling which is like in a mobile mobile
phone or or diving instrumental or this
kind of advanced words we have with a
number of features like the stopwatch or
have timer timer alarm oh I was I was
joking because that's your standards
five million times yes yes well we used
the digital resource an example because
everybody knows the time and everybody
usually owns except Marcos home watch
but people can people know how it how do
and you can you can build surprisingly
many yeah applications have that like
they we were discussing a watch so for
for people when they're paying a chess
yeah they can see in the how much each
time players press the right so you can
build enormous number of different
product lines like like the watch
industries - yeah right yeah another
case that restriction that he has been
talking about in the episode where we
interviewed him obviously was that you
might have a framework and you want to
provide a nice DSL took to configure the
framework yes and in that case you would
derive the language from the framework
or in some sense it's the same thing as
with your forklift but but it's but it's
now software that you derive it from and
not a physical device we would call that
if i underscore ectly
is it you
you you look what is your existing API
is what is the exiting code and then you
abstract from there languages but
there's also place to warn in this kind
of situation is that you may end up in
this way into a language which has a low
abstraction levels but added with the
rules right use that lower abstraction
level and an increased of course the
stuff a framework specific modeling
language in which case the lobe
structure but of course in the worst
place it is that for each API yes you
have one language concept which is
horrible solution player but maybe you
can analyze that further to see what is
the underlying programming model how
those frameworks are you right and then
you can abstract further and to come
back to the model to model
transformation thing sorry you can use
that framework specific or technology
specific modeling language at the bottom
and then you build your higher levels of
abstraction then that there are more
domain-specific and use a model to model
transformation to go down to that
existing one and that makes a lot of
sense if there is if there is a lot of
very intricate coding patterns in the
generator like in many embedded
applications you have all kinds of
pointer crap and you know so you want to
abstract that layer so that it's clean
and then you can generate or transform
to that layer it's another example where
Antfarm is useful yes but again there's
some alternative ways to solve that just
just to work with that the example you
mentioned you may have a higher level
language that someone specifies if then
you change the metamodel for that high
level language which is more expressive
power yeah and then it you give it for
other people let's say you have people
who do high level user interface
specification that and they use a
language and specify the behavior of the
system in a general view yep then you
give that like a model to the technical
people who who analyze it further
details and change the metamodel behind
which is a component with this earlier
metamodel yep but then you don't do any
more model to model transformation you
don't use the same model you just
changed the metamodel and then people
can continue with be working with the
same model with for further details yeah
that's another way which there
if people see how to to work with the
models at different type of users with
different levels of knowledge yeah you
mentioned that those insurance guys had
a mouth based metamodel available
unfortunately yes
and I noticed your opinion there that
you're not that much of a fan of Mothe
so don't you use morph as the m3 level
as the meta meta mono we don't know but
the problem with them with using a more
force that the more version was changing
so even though this was done in two
months they quickly shocked out now we
need to start again because something
has changed which is which is nothing to
do with this whole thing but just to
follow this pride that the other thing
that they had the problem with this was
but then the the meta molar became
surprisingly complex because they wanted
to include all the stuff on the move to
the underlying language and we want to
say please you don't need these yeah but
that's a design mistake yes no yeah but
it caused you to do it guides you to
specify for each language concept is
this abstract is this rule and all that
stuff yeah well we don't we don't use
move maybe partly because we are using a
repository based approach to build these
tools so we define the data structure
and we did our work before the form of
here and we did our work based on other
tools that already worked like a quick
spec or SPN CSP SLA which work at 70s
and 80s as a meta systems so we try to
build on something what works rather
than build something on I found a nice
paper what except for the standards
versus working what's the what's that
the difference in my opinion the morph
is pretty complex and all the tool
vendors who tried to implement or part
of that have ended up on implementing
little bit something yes and they call
it then maybe Exmoor for whatever almost
like or whatever but we have for
instance a specific concept of language
in a meta mean language so we have only
six concepts in our meta model and one
of these cons is language so we can
two people now - look how languages can
be combined how we can hierarchical
structure language is to have a SAP
models based on different language which
move doesn't guide you at all it's
possible but it doesn't guide you that's
your point yes
with this t.o.p or methanol that we have
using we also can guide people to do the
metamoris let's look look you have
specified relationships but they are not
buying it correctly yeah we can look in
our relationships so we can have a
connection from one object to multiple
objects at the same time so if the
connection change we only change it one
place rather than drawing the line for
500 times for each by 50 times for in
each emergency state and give specific
properties for these 50 lines but in our
case you would actually draw one line
for those 50 if you would do that way
and all the blocks all the properties
all the properties of that line will
only enter runs at the point you still
have 50 lines but there would be more
elected in one point at which core and
that you would have a line ends right
the the associate if you would do that
theme yeah the Association would be to
pictorial the speaking would be a bubble
that contains all the properties and
then you connect this to n yes any no
case it's not Nestle bubble is how you
how you want to eat represent it can be
just a line - of course okay so the next
example is this mobile point-of-sale
which I really like because so it's
basically about building a PDA based
sales application and the language you
use for defining how the application
works uses the same syntax more or less
as the final application correct the the
reason why this works is because your
editor framework allows you to have
really nice interactive pictures we want
to talk about that a little bit yes of
course I would like to speak up without
product you don't have to I mean you can
talk about well in this particular case
we we basically when we start to discuss
how to get domain concepts of difference
time you mentioned this framework based
approach I also measured it it's look
and feel based approach this is an
example of that that you dairy of your
language con
from your view from the end-product
right so we have here notation that
looks like the running system in a
mobile phone like widgets combo boxes
exactly and also the navigation close
but they also other nice things like
like people rather than writing the code
for for this concept of login so they
shall log in a application the beginning
the journey to do rather than specifying
the code for locking in our modeling
language there's now only one object
called login yeah
if abstract it doesn't have any
properties you just say that I would
like to login and you add this I orange
L rounded simple to the drawing area and
then you connect to the next step like
here to the main menu structure that
means then that you would like to have
it locking in your application and then
go to the main menu yep
and of course to make sure people don't
think we're doing advertising here the
point we're trying to make I think is
the abstraction yes abstraction that's
the logging thing that's one thing but
the other thing is that in order to get
acceptance for you DSL with your users
you should try to make sure the language
uses visual syntax that is as close as
possible to what they have been working
with before correct that's here the UI
thing and in case of the insurance stuff
with intentional just to elaborate on
that and Capgemini this prototype
they've publicly talked about the the
idea was to take their existing language
which they had before in Word documents
and stuff and just formalize the
language and build a tool around it and
again so people users were working with
staff that had been working with before
but now with a much better tool and much
better constraint checks and much better
automation at the back category
sometimes a very good source for forum
for the concrete syntax is the
powerpoints people do yeah many people
do powerpoints but when they do use
powerpoints for design then they are
totally free to choose whatever design
style they feel suitable for that task
and if then they realize the number of
people start to use PowerPoint similarly
then obviously there's some reason
behind the the vocabulary and probably
the way they specify things with
PowerPoint so in a cool situation you
can take the notation from the
PowerPoint and put the structure there F
behind your language and then you can
give it to back for them and they think
I said you can continue specifying your
powerpoints but now you can also produce
running products
I was once involved in a project mobile
phone industry where we build a
prototype for doing something similar
with of course auto tooling but it
doesn't matter so and I went to this
customer and they said you know we I
mean we do have quite a good
understanding of our system and he comes
around comes with this Visio file
yes which had like 200 visual diagrams
they had even created a their own shapes
their own palette and they were
specifying the requirements of a
specifying their applications by
visually composing their custom shapes
and these shapes of course would be box
drop-down button and then they took that
literally once they draw the picture
printed and people implemented it
manually and I thought guys you can't do
this why don't you generate it's exactly
the same case right yes okay and the
next two or three examples are basically
process descriptions right the first one
is about the voice of a voice
application which is your college menu
yes boys menu there is two different
type of diagrams mm-hmm there's the
high-level view for the system and then
each individual loudspeaker looking
symbols are described in this other
diagram in more detail like voice
interaction eyes boys interactions and
and then the coaching right to basically
reach the models from the top diagram
and goes into these sub diagrams to
produce code out and this is a case of
8-bit microcontroller so very important
for them was to save the memory so it
also looks if the same strings are a
multiple time repeated in the light
lives in the voice menus and then use
the same memory addresses for that
strings but the code that's Jerry
Radley uses a specific language does
this speak things there are Pro off they
own yes their own so you could argue
that is one of those framework specific
modeling language is this language
already existed and you have built a
nicer more user-friendly tooling on top
of it yeah you could say so yes the next
example is a telecom service
configuration language and as people
probably know a services in telecom with
all this quality of service stuff are
quite complex so what did you do in this
case what what's the reason for building
that language actually we don't know
okay because because the customer made
it all by themselves huh okay they asked
that a couple of emails and then okay
did okay um what they want to do is that
obviously deriding these configuration
scripts manually so error-prone because
of implied pecan strike it was implied
contract because they are using it in a
running system yeah so they want to be
sure that they are configured correctly
and they realize that they're repeating
same kind of patterns yep and that's the
abstract it to the modeling language yes
and then having rules in that modeling
language they can be sure then that the
specifications they do for service
configuration are correct yeah at least
to some extent correct yeah so the point
was abstraction and also in some sense
aesthetic constraint checking instead of
doing it you know putting the stuff in
the in e-file and watch the system crash
because you did something wrong you put
the rule in the language and you don't
you can either yes yes yes that's also
very good use case but many domain speak
languages has always this error
prevention yes aspect here at the
earlier week we can route to the rule to
the language the earlier we can prevent
illegal designs or designs that lead to
poor performance yeah and then they also
cheap is to correct because I not even
followed him to happen and of course
also because the error messages are part
of the DSL and they use domain specific
terminology as opposed to out of memory
error yes right if you crash in the in
the Lal of the system so it also makes
the the the potential errors more
convenient to for fro users the next one
is something I've seen you I think demo
or Isis I've seen your customer demo at
the other guy sniper conference at some
point I think it's about infotainment
systems that's you
you know radio video mobile phone in the
car yes and they are getting today
extremely complex as the luxury cars can
have up to 1000 menus in an in a car so
obviously someone must design them
carefully what they mean yeah and in
this part of your case what is
interesting is that there's actually a
tree different views the viewpoints like
like you served yeah sub languages sub
languages so these are people who have
let's say the artists who define the
layout part
what are the colors fonts icons themes
so what it looks like yep then there are
other people who have another viewpoint
another meta malala language who specify
the individual displays for the system
so they how they use the screen estate F
correctly yeah and intuitively and that
information they use and specify is
again applied by another viewpoint where
they are describing the interaction with
the system yep and if someone now
changed is the the the content part on
the individual static display structures
those changes can be reflected
automatically to those who specify the
behavior yeah so if they add something
to the display then the people who are
specifying the behavior can see that now
we need to add new functionality because
station you visualization available and
so forth and they do this for generating
the code usually an automotive they do
some coaching race let's say in a
browser in Java F that take any quickly
prototype and try it out whether it's
like sense simulator simulator and
automotive industry works today so that
they stand subcontractors first level
second level who didn't do the final
implementation but basically nothing
prevents to change the code generator
from Java to the to the native let's say
see the element ations a little bit
about trust yes and party maybe also the
rules how the
the industry works so for example if you
are generating part of the code first
Java I work wonderfully there and then
you would like to say the same system
now in C please but if you generate the
code from the models that the let's say
the brand created the automotive
manufacturer created and then you asked
subcontractors to do the implementation
by using the generated code who who
actually takes responsibility of the
generated C called air which posed the
target yeah I really think this this um
this idea of multiple viewpoints or
multiple sub languages kind of extremely
useful I mean not that this is something
I just noticed but it's important to
communicate yes okay so I guess this
this was or these were some of the
interesting examples I guess
those case studies that are publicly
available we'll put links in the show
notes is there anything else you want to
say so to wrap up this this thing slowly
but certainly I would like to basically
mention that companies who have tried
these kind of domain-specific languages
say usually that there's a product is
increases if a fundamental yep
some companies say that lets say panels
only grow the work paper to the books or
workshop that they claim to be now
making same application of 500 percent
faster that would be five times five
times faster and Nokia claims that there
may be in making now product line and
mobile phone they are making it 10 times
faster compared to earlier manual yeah
practice so it's a huge huge improvement
and what's your experience in the
initial investment because I mean you
have to build languages generators and
stuff yes so how much I mean how do how
does this stack up how is there any
metrics you can give we have tried to
measure of course right all this
information what we have it but we have
also noticed that the circumstances or
the background for the company cases are
always a little bit different right of
direct completion is is difficult but we
have find out that code generator
usually takes more time than making the
metamodel
for sure concrete syntax sometimes taken
more time than making the
yeah because until until the vein that
you have really nice-looking a very
document generated and so forth you can
do a lot of effort there yeah most of
the time and company seems to have with
with the underlying frameworks so if
they have a product line which is
actually a copy of the earlier product
then it's more difficult to apply code
generators if the if the basis and the
foundation is not they're not there but
if companies have already realized we
have a reusable components yeah we have
a reusable pieces of or we have a
component factories a team who do come
on yeah platform platform team is always
suspicious yes then then and then
there's a good chance yeah but because
of these quite huge product if you
increase or even academically proven of
cases yep my my summary would be active
for people to try out of different tools
and try to out-build domains basic
languages and take the low-hanging
through its first so pick those cases
where you can show immediate benefits
even though you may feel that they are
too small and you would see more
interesting yeah thing to tackle but you
can do that later I mean what's your
weight when it management when you wanna
means your colleagues if you don't
believe that you can generate code yes
or you can convince your miniatures if
they say wow this gave a good return of
investment let's let's use this more
yeah so easy case first and then if
there are help from people or discussion
groups yep or even tool vendors or
consultants who feel free to use those
trust that they provide such a service
especially consultants okay so JP thank
you very much for being on the show I
think it was an interesting discussion
okay thank you your own pleasure the
video
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SE radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at SD - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the positive music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]